For this module I'm back in the application or the project we worked on in the last core section and you
can find my state attached to this video so that you can start right at the same point as I do.
So it is just the code we wrote over the last lectures
and one thing we constantly had to do in the last section or throughout this course was that we always
had to run node app.js to start our well app or our node application with that file.
Now this is certainly ok and not too much work but it actually is possible to define some scripts in
a nodejs project that can help us with tasks like this,
we can also use them for other tasks but especially for this, they can be useful right now
and for that we have to use a feature we didn't use thus far.
We have to use npm, npm stands for node package manager and it is installed together with nodejs, so
you don't need to do anything,
you got this installed already.
Now we will also use npm to install some additional third party packages to our project soon, so packages
that are not included in nodes core,
so not part of nodes core modules but we can also use npm to initialize a so-called node project or
to add some extra features to it
to be precise because we obviously already got a node project here but now in this project, in a terminal
navigated into this project, you can run npm init.
Now this will not delete your code or anything like that,
no worries,
simply hit enter and you'll be prompted with a couple of questions here.
It'll ask you first of all for a name of your package
and for now you can simply translate this with project name.
Now you can pick any name you want, the part in the parentheses here
always is the suggestion, the default
it will pick if you don't choose your own name,
so if I just hit enter here, it will take that default.
So you can basically do that for all these questions,
for the description, you can leave that empty
then it will have no default text either but you can also enter some text like complete nodejs
guide, this is what this course is and then define an entry point with fs for example. You can leave
the task command empty, leave that empty, keywords you can choose some if you want,
you can put your name into the offer field though this is also not required and you can always choose
a license
but if you don't plan on sharing this project publicly,
this also doesn't really matter.
So with this what you get is this package.json file and there you also see all these settings
or configurations you just set up and you can of course edit them there too,
so if you had a typo in your description, you can just edit it here.
Now this is using the json format which is a special kind of data format which basically looks a
lot like javascript objects and it pretty much is based on that,
there is one important thing to understand though,
the keys are always put between double quotation marks and so are the values, except for numbers or arrays
or true or false which are not put between these
but that's too much
for now, we can ignore that for now just so that you understand what you got there,
it's basically a configuration file for your project.
Now what does this configuration file give you?
Well let's clear the console here,
with this configuration file, you'll see that we got a scripts section there which has one default script
that won't do anything for now,
you can add your own scripts here and I will tell you how to execute them too of course.
For that, let's add a comma after this test script and add a new script name which has to be put between
double quotation marks and there, let's name it start. Now
start is actually a special script name as you will see in a second,
so make sure to type this correctly and then between the quotation marks,
you type a command that should be executed.
So this is a command which you could also type down there
and there we always have to type
node app.js,
so let's now put that between these double quotation marks here
like this.
With that save that file
and then you can run npm start. Start is a reserved name and this will always look for such a start
script here.
And if you do that, it will as you can see here just execute node app.js.
So it does the same you had before but now you can always just well run this command instead of running
node
app.js. Not that much of a saved characters but a few at least
and it's also a good practice because if you ever share this project,
it's pretty common that people just have to run npm start and that they don't have to guess which of your
javascript files is the entry file.
So you can quit this with control c of course as always and I mentioned that this would be a special
script name.
You can add more scripts, also without using a special name,
you can indeed choose any name you want,
just make sure to always wrap the name in double quotation marks and that it does not contain any blanks
or whitespaces.
So for example we could have start-server.
Now this can also run node app.js,
so it will do the exact same as this script and therefore it's of course redundant
but I want to show you something
and now if you try running npm start-server, you'll get an error.
You basically get an error that is not a known command and indeed it isn't because just typing
the script name here will not work,
start
just was the special case as I mentioned.
Indeed for normal scripts with their own custom names, you have to run npm run and then your script name,
so npm run start-server will now also start the server.
Now as I mentioned, this is of course redundant, npm start is way shorter but I want you to understand
how you can add your own scripts.
Now if you worked with something like angular or react or vue or any modern frontend development workflow,
you will have seen that you use such scripts a lot to trigger build workflows for your projects for
example and indeed you can use that for all kinds of tasks to want to execute
but for now we'll not dive deeper into that and if you haven't worked with angular or react, it's
also
no problem,
you will see what I mean
later in this course when I explore node's functionality as a build tool a bit more.
For now let's just use that npm start script to start our application conveniently.