So in the last lecture, we added a script to start our application and this is nice to know that we
have this scripting functionality. Now with such a package.json file available,
so therefore with this being a managed node project you could say, we can also do one other very important thing,
we can install third party packages because a typical node project looks like that. You have your local
project with your code obviously and you use a lot of core node packages like the fs package or the http
package we're already using
but often this does not suffice
and in the next core section, we will install one big third package actually because you typically have
such dependencies third party packages.
So you want to use some functionalities some code which you didn't write on your own but which is also
not included into nodejs. Packages could help you with parsing incoming requests, validating user input,
anything of that kind.
Now we will use express in the next lectures or in the next module to be precise, body parser is another
package we'll use throughout this course and there are thousands of packages available that offer all
kinds of utilities you can add to your projects
so that you don't have to reinvent the wheel.
These packages are available through the npm repository,
that is a cloud package repository where all these packages live
and you can conveniently install and manage them via npm,
remember that tool that shipped with node. And this is exactly what we will do now to install a first
little utility package that will speed up our development workflow.
Because right now what we have to do is whenever we change our code, we have to quit the development
server with Control-C and restart it,
right,
so if we have it running with npm start now, remember this is our new command to start the server
and I would change something here, like for example here I fixed that /head right,
whenever I do this I have to save this and for my change to have an effect, I have to quit the server
with Control-C and restart it.
Now this is a bit cumbersome because we just want to be able to type and then hit save
and it should automatically restart and right, that would be a great workflow during development and
to achieve this, we have to install a third party package that gives us just this functionality.
Now how do we add such a third party package?
We do that with the help of npm and there, we get the install command,
so just as we had run to run one of our scripts, install installs a third party package.
Now how do we install it?
First of all we have to know the package name
and if you're wondering well how do I know the package name,
well that comes with courses like this, experience or by simply googling for certain problems which
you want to have solved and all of a sudden you find a thread where some package is mentioned.
Now I can tell you for this auto-restart mechanism,
there is a package called nodemon, written like this.
By the way you can always search for npm and then the package name if you know that name and you will
find an entry on npmjs.com.
Now this is the package page basically where you find a description, installation instructions, usage
instructions, how to configure it because most packages give you an easy way of using it and then always
give you configuration possibilities.
You'll see how popular the package is,
what's version it's using, if there is an exernal little home page, where the source code can be found if
it's open source.
So you find a bunch of stuff here, pretty useful,
you also see how many versions are existing
and by default, you will always install the latest version by the way
but let's go back to installing it
before we dive deeper into this whole npm thing.
So we want to install it and this command would install it
but don't hit enter yet,
you can define how this should be installed because packages which you install can be divided into development
packages, so packages which mostly help you during development and production dependencies,
so packages that helps you for the app as it's running on a server, for example nodemon would be a
development dependency because we only use it during the development process,
once we install our app on a real server we don't need it there.
The real server which is running somewhere in the Internet of course shouldn't restart
and it also doesn't have to because we'll not change its code dynamically.
And you can basically tell npm which kind of dependency this is, this does not make a huge difference
and you can omit the setting but it helps you understand which package is used for what. Now you do add this
by adding --save-dev,
if you had just save like this, this would install it as a production dependency,
so a package which we really use and use in our code and work with and with this we're indicating that
this only adds something we used during development.
There also is a third option by the way,
-g, we'll not install it in this project but globally on your machine
so that you can use it anywhere.
Now let's first of all install it with save dev, like this --save-dev.
Now what this will do is it will download it from the npm repository and install it into this project,
so not globally on your machine but into this project.
So now you see you get a report here that it finished successfully, what it did and it gives you a couple
of new things in your project.
It gives you that node modules folder, the package log json file and it updated the package.json
file.
There we see that the new dev dependency section was added and that stands for development dependencies,
as I said you can differentiate between different dependencies,
we'll see production dependencies later too
and there you see that nodemon was installed and which version was picked.
Now regarding that character here,
well this basically defines how this package will be updated
if you rerun just npm install, without defining an extra package name because this command standalone
will simply go through all your packages mentioned in package.json and install them and it would automatically
pick a later version if available
but more on npm and packages can also be found in a separate module
later in the course.
So this is basically how we now install this
and the question is where is it installed?
Well that is the node modules folder
and actually that is a huge folder as you can tell. The reason for this is that
for one we got nodemon in there,
if we look for n, we see it here.
Now this is basically the source code of the package or the build version of the package we installed
and this package simply happens to have a couple of peer dependencies,
you can see them here and here.
So we got a bunch of dependencies in there and these and their dependencies are also installed,
that is why you could end up with quite a big node modules folder but you can always delete that node
modules folder if you need to free up space.
Now you can't use that package but you can then rerun npm install if you start working on that project
again and it will re-install this package and all its pure dependencies and therefore recreate the node
modules folder,
this is how packages work in node projects.
So you need that node modules folder while still using the packages but if you're not working on the
project, you can delete it if you want, if you need the free space and then just remember to rerun npm
install once you are working on the project again.
The package log json file by the way just stores the exact versions I installed today so that if you
share your project with others, they can actually get these exact versions too instead of the latest versions
but again, more on npm in a separate module.