So for now we got that nodemon package installed and it will just work because it automatically installed
all the dependencies
this package needs in turn.
So how can we now use it?
Nodemon is a utility tool and it allows us to run our application, our node application through this
package here which will run node apps.js
in the end but which will also watch our files for changes and restart the process for us if
we do change something. So we can simply change start here,
so the node app.js command to nodemon app.js
and this will look for a nodemon tool which it will find in this project because we installed it
here. As a side note
if you were to run nodemon app.js down there, you would get an error that this command is not found
because it's only installed in this project and not globally on your machine but the terminal will try
to find this globally. Here
it will work because this will look globally.
So if you now run npm start, this will simply start the node server and output some extra information
and if you now go to your routes.js file and edit something,
let's just add an extra line and you save that file, you see it's restarting.
And this of course is very convenient because now, we dont have to spend time on manually exiting and
restarting,
now is this done for us.