Syntax errors can be very annoying
but most of the time, they're not that hard to fix.
Let's add a simple syntax error, here in app.js let's simply remove the t in const,
now all of a sudden, this is an invalid keyword,
it doesn't exist, it's not a keyword
and we already get some help in the IDE which is showing us something is wrong here.
Now if we hover over this, we see that a semi-colon is expected
and actually this is not that helpful
and this is simply because visual studio code thinks so that this is a variable
and since we have a variable in the same line, we should close this with a semi-colon
and now it actually doesn't show an error. But let's save this and let's try running our app with npm
start without that semi-colon we added. And you will see, it right away
crashes and in there we see unexpected identifier const server.
So in the end, whilst it doesn't clearly tell us that we forgot the t here because it's not smart enough
to understand that this is the error here,
we still see that the error seems to be stemming from this line
and in such cases, as dumb as it sounds, you should simply take a closer look at this line and see what
could be wrong there
and you should quickly be able to see
I forgot a t here.
So these are syntax errors,
other errors would be that you maybe go to the routes.js file and let's say you forget a closing curly
brace here.
Now again visual studio code does complain and does show an error over there,
if we jump there we see at the end that the closing curly brace is expected.
Now it's not expected at this point where it's showing this message but it's expected somewhere in the
file and whilst it can be cumbersome,
you should then check your block statements like this if statement and see if there are all closed correctly.
In visual studio code, you also get some help because if you click next to such a curly brace, you'll see
that this line gets highlighted and it actually shows you where it thinks that this is getting closed
and this is far too much at the bottom here
for example. Again if you run this, you will see that it crashes and there, you also see unexpected token
and it points us at routes.js
.
and then you see the line number too.
So here it points us at line 52 and it basically shows us the same place as visual studio code which
is the wrong place
but in such a case here, you should really take the IDE help, see that error message and then go through
your file and see
hmm where could I be missing a character or where do I have an extra closing curly brace or something
like that
and eventually you should be able to find this error and therefore of course fix it.
So syntax errors should always result in an error message and then that can sometimes be hard to find
them,
often it's like a typo, a mistyped variable name of a variable that therefore doesn't exist or missing
or extra characters but you can find them and it just takes some time to go through your file.