The next category are runtime errors and a great example for this can be shown with the res write method
here.
Now as I mentioned, you have to return here to prevent the execution of the code after this statement
otherwise and this is something node specific of course, you would
end a request here but the code execution would continue
and eventually we would reach this line and this is no syntax error,
this is correct but if we run our code here, seems to work right,
there is no syntax error after all.
But if we now visit our page, eventually it breaks here and this is the point where it should go back
to your code and should find an error message there too. And this error message is something you
shouldn't just take and paste into the Q & A section but actually read it.
A lot of the error messages are indeed helpful,
you just need to know how to read them, at the bottom
you always find uninteresting stuff I'd say but you have to scroll to the top of the error message and
all of a sudden, it should get more meaningful.
For example here, you see the error code which already indicates that it's something with headers being
sent and then here, you actually find a detailed error message, cannot set headers after they are set
to the client and then you see that it was caused by a call to set header and unfortunately, the line
numbers don't help you, here at least
but then it does help you here,
you see it's in the request handler and there it points at the routes.js file line 32. And now this is the
point where you can dive in and see,
ok I'm calling set header here,
now since it's complaining that I can't set them after they are sent to the client,
I should look well in the code before this statement because it looks like I'm finishing my response
there for this example. And indeed at some point you should find this statement and see I do actually
not finish my code execution after this statement which is not per se a problem but it becomes a problem
if in the following code, I then work on my response again as I'm doing it here.
So now this is the point where we can fix this by stopping the code execution or by wrapping this in an
extra if statement which is guaranteed to not run
if we make it into this statement. And now with that, we can of course restart our server
or actually we don't need to,
we got nodemon now so you don't need to do that
and now if you reload your page, it will work again.