Now the third kind of error I want to discuss is the logical error and that is often the most difficult
one to fix because it will not cause an error message,
your app will just not behave the way you expect it to.
Let's see here in the routes.js file where we parse our body, we're retrieving the message here and
that is of course nice but let's say I actually do have the first element being stored in message here
and keep in mind the second element which we previously had is the actual message the user entered because
we're splitting that key value pair we're getting automatically and now we're actually storing the wrong
element.
So now if I save this and my server restarts due to nodemon, I can enter some test here
and if I do this and I open my message text file, I actually see message there.
Now this is a logical error because we got no error message
but the app is not behaving the way we want it to.
Now of course we know that we used the wrong index here because I just changed that
but let's say you worked on that code for the first time and you just use zero here because you forgot
that this should be one,
so you didn't change that back on purpose but you really made this mistake.
Now it's not super obvious to see
and how can you now work on such errors?
Well with the help of the nodejs
debugger which actually has a great integration into visual studio code which I strongly recommend
using.
Let me show you how that debugger works then.
For this, let's quit that process and let's select the app.js file now, that's important
and now go to debug here in visual studio code in the menu and choose start debugging or use the keyboard
shortcut you see there.
Now with that, you have to choose an environment and there you should use nodejs and you will now see
that extra bar here at the top which allows you to control the debugger, you see the red bar at the bottom
that indicates that you're in debugging mode and you actually also have a debug console here where you
now see that the debugger is attached and listening.
Now what does this mean?
This means that now you actually can look into your code as it's running
but to really do that, you need to set so-called breakpoints.
So let's go to the route.js file
and let's say we assume it has something to do our error here with the wrong text being stored with
this code snippet because ultimately, that is where we write it to the file.
So what you can do is you can set a breakpoint in visual studio code by going to the left of the line
numbers until you see that red dot and clicking there.
Now we got a breakpoint there and what will now happen is that with that debugging process running, don't
quit this, you can quit it by clicking the red square but let's leave it running,
if you now submit some text here, it should automatically jump back and mark this line like this, highlighted
yellow and kind of put this yellow arrow around our breakpoint.
This means that the code execution now stopped here,
it did not continue,
it stopped and it stopped
so that you can look inside of it and actually you can now analyze your code in the moment it's running.
For example you can hover over your variables to see what's stored inside of them,
so for example you see that the parsed body is this string which we're splitting in the yellow highlighted line.
You see what's inside of the body you passed to concat, that it's an array with a buffer of length 12
for example.
You can even expand this to look into it a bit more and find more details about the buffer, in case you're
interested here.
You also can go to view and then debug here,
this gives you a special debug mode where you see the key variables you have available in your code
right now,
message is undefined because we stopped in that line where we would set it
but it stops before it executes the line,
so therefore message is still undefined at this point
but parsed body for example does hold the value, well it has which you can also see if you hover over
it.
You don't just see local variables which are available in this function but block variables too, this is
the variable which is always available outside of this function,
it's this variable
and you can also look into that therefore and you can generally click around to see some global values
and the values they currently have stored
and a couple of these things. You also can define watchers here,
for example you can click a plus here and then watch message and hit enter
and now you will always see that here, you also see it up here
but if you ever close that, you can define some variables you're particularly interested in and watch them
whilst you go through your code. And you also see your breakpoints down there,
you see all the breakpoints you set,
you can uncheck them here to not stop execution the next time they are reached and so on.
You also see the call stack which looks very cryptic but what in the end just shows how the process went
through your code and you can click on these different parts to see where actually this code which belongs
to the code that was executed can be found and not all of that is code you wrote, a lot of that is core
nodejs code.
Ok
so that's the debugger in a nutshell.
Now to work it and to continue with your code execution,
you can use that panel here at the top.
You can resume code execution with the play button but we don't want to do that
instead we want to step through our code step by step so that we can see when it fails or where it goes
wrong.
And you can do that with this button which steps to the next line basically or with this button here
which doesn't just step into the next line
but actually even goes into functions like this one.
So if you click here and again, now all of a sudden you're in the write file function defined by nodejs
and you can step out of there with this key. Now you see if you continue here that this wasn't too helpful
but that we can now navigate like this in our code.
So now let's make this more helpful
and for that, let's try this again and use that debugger properly now.
We'll do this in the next lecture.