There's one more feature about the nodejs debugger which I also haven't shown you yet but which I of course
don't want to forget. If you start debugging here
and here I just use the shortcut and you place a breakpoint anywhere in your app and then do something
to trigger that breakpoint,
I showed you that you can look into all these variables and that you can look into them in the debug
console without changing them. Well sometimes you might want to change them
and that can be done by going to the debug view here and then by simply typing in there.
Now for example, the parsed body holds this string and you can't just change it
and now this will affect the runtime as you can see if you hover over this.
So now if I just resume execution with my code which doesn't have a bug right now and I go back to
my explorer view here, then you will see that I stored testing here which is the value I edited
in the debugger. So you can actually manipulate the values there of the variables and so on if you need
to,
you can do that because this of course allows you to make sure that you can quickly test something.
This is just another useful feature which I wanted to share with you since it can help you with debugging
your code, being able to manipulate some values there.